<?xml version='1.0'?>

<project>
  <name>SSA: Sparse Surface Adjustment 2D</name>

  <author>
    <name>Michael Ruhnke</name>
    <url>http://www.informatik.uni-freiburg.de/~ruhnke</url>
  </author>
  <author>
    <name>Rainer Kuemmerle</name>
    <url>http://www.informatik.uni-freiburg.de/~kuemmerl</url>
  </author>
  <author>
    <name>Giorgio Grisetti</name>
    <url>http://www.informatik.uni-freiburg.de/~grisetti</url>
  </author>
  <author>
    <name>Wolfram Burgard</name>
    <url>http://www.informatik.uni-freiburg.de/~burgard/</url>
  </author>

  <briefdescription>
    SSA is an open-source C++ tool for post optimization of graph-based 2D SLAM
    solutions. SSA iteratively refines robot poses and 2D surface points in one 
    global graph optimization system and produces highly accurate 2D laser maps.
    Laser scans are not treated as rigid body and might be refined during the
    optimization procedure. This leads to substantially less accumulated noise 
    in the resulting map. SSA uses g2o as optimization back-end. 
  </briefdescription>
  
  <description>
    The goal of Sparse Surface Adjustment 2D is to learn highly accurate 
    laser-based maps. Therefore it treats the overall mapping problem as a joint 
    optimization problem over robot poses and laser points. 
    Under the assumption that a laser range finder measures points sampled 
    from a regular surface this algorithm utilize an improved likelihood 
    function that accounts for two phenomena affecting the laser measurements 
    that are often neglected: the conic shape of the laser beam and the 
    incidence angle of a beam on the underlying surface. A maximum likelihood
    configuration of all robot poses and all points is computed with g2o.
    Since the data association is hard to solve on points only, SSA iteratively 
    updates the data association and local surface characteristics.
    
    Sample datasets can be downloaded at:
    http://www.informatik.uni-freiburg.de/~ruhnke/
  </description>

  <requirement>
    Developed under Linux (GCC). Tested under Linux.
    CMake is needed for building. Uses SuiteSparse if available, requires Qt4
    and libQGLViewer for the GUI. Furthermore libkdtree++ is needed.
    Includes a copy of g2o.
  </requirement>

  <map>Graphs (nodes and edge)</map>

  <input>
    Nodes and edges of a graph.
  </input>

  <logformat>
    A set of simple text messages to represent nodes and edges of the graph.
    Note that examples files are in the repository. See folder data.
  </logformat>

  <paper>
    <title>Highly Accurate Maximum Likelihood Laser Mapping by Jointly Optimizing Laser Points and Robot Poses</title>
    <authorlist>Michael Ruhnke, Rainer Kuemmerle, Giorgio Grisetti and Wolfram Burgard</authorlist>
    <publishedin>IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)</publishedin>
    <year>2011</year>
    <url>http://ais.informatik.uni-freiburg.de/publications/papers/ruhnke11icra.pdf</url>
  </paper>

  <license>ssa is licenced under LGPL v3</license>

  <furthermore>
    C++ code, well-coded, compact, efficient.
  </furthermore>

</project>
